Guide to the James Hogg Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
James Hogg collection
1803-1836
GEN MSS 61
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.8
(2 boxes) + 1 oversize Gaylord
Letters by James Hogg to various persons; one letter by Margaret Phillips Hogg and one by William Hogg; manuscripts of writings by James Hogg, including "Memoir of Burns," and "Tales of Fathers and Daughters by the Ettrick Shepherd"; one drawing of James Hogg.
Hogg, James, 1770-1835
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ongoing collection of documents acquired by gift and purchase from various sources. Type of accession (gift or purchase) and date of acquisition is noted in the box-and-folder list. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Existence and Location of Copies
Microfilm available for manuscript items: "Julia M'Kenzie" (bound with "Wat Pringle o' the Yair") [folder 49] and "Mary Montgomery" [folder 25].
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses accessions of single manuscripts and small groups of manuscripts and other papers, by or pertaining to James Hogg, which the library has chosen to group and list as an artificial collection. Materials incorporated into the collection prior to June 1997 have been organized into 2 series. The first series contains items given to the library in 1931 by R. B. Adam. The second series contains subsequent gifts from other parties and purchases. Materials added to the collection since that time are located in Series III, Additions since June 1997, listed in the order in which they were added.
Poets, Scottish -- 19th century; Hogg, James, 1770-1835
- Materials given by R. B. Adam, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Gift, 1931
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - Hogg, James
      - Letter (copy in an unidentified hand) to James Anderson, London, 1832 Mar 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - ALS to Bernard Barton, Edinburgh 1813 Jun 7 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - ALS to S[imeon] DeWitt Bloodgood, Altrive by Selkirk, 1833 [Jun] 22 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - ALS to James Brown, 1831 Jul 20 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - ALS to [George Gordon Noël Byron] Lord Byron, Yarrow, 1814 Jun 3 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - 6 ALS to James Cochrane, Altrive Lake, 1832-1835 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - 4 ALS to Allan Cunningham, Mount Benger and Altrive Lake, 1828-1834 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - ALS to Alexander Elder, Altrive [Lake], 1833 Jan 14 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - 2 ALS to George Glenny, Altrive lake, 1831, 1832 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - 2 ALS to S[amuel C[arter] Hall, Mount Benger, 1830, 1835 (Box 1, Folder 10)
        The letter of 1835 contains a poem entitled "To Miss M.A. C--e By the Ettrick Shepherd."
      - ALS to Messrs. Goulding & D[']Almaine, Mount Benger by Selkirk, 1829 Mar 17 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - ANS to Neil Gow, [Edinburgh], [1819] May 21 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - 3 ALS to Eliza Izet, Locherben by Thornhill and Edinburgh, 1803-1813 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - ALS to [the editor of The Scotsman], Edinburgh, [1818] May 17 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - ALS to [R. A.] Smith [unidentified], Edinburgh, n.d. [1818-1825] (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - ALS to George Thomson, [Edinburgh], [1814 Nov 28] (Box 1, Folder 16)
        Endorsed
      - ALS to [Roscoe and Richie?], London, 1832 Mar 19 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Hogg, Margaret (Phillips)
      - ALS to James Cochrane, Altrive Lake, 1836 Jan 30 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Hogg, William
      - Letter (copy in an unidentifiable hand) and ALS to James Gray, containing recollections of the youth of the Hogg brothers, 1813 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - WRITINGS
    - Hogg, James
      - "Ah loveliest of the lowly throng", Mount Benger, 1829 Jan 29 (Box 1, Folder 20)
        First line of an autograph manuscript poem written in couplets
      - Three sketches: autograph manuscript containing "The Dirty Wean", "The History of an Auld Naig" and "David Wilkie", 1829 Aug 7 (Box 1, Folder 21)
        Addressed to S. C. Hall, Esq., Westley and Davies, London
      - A HORRIBLE INSTANCE OF THE RIGHTS OF A CLAN-SHIP: autograph MS (incomplete), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 22)
        The bottom half of the MS has been torn away
      - THE HUNTING OF BADLEWE BY J.H. CRAIG ESQR. [pseud.]: autograph MS, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - JOCK ARMSTRONG: autograph MS tale, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - JULIA M'KENZIE: autograph MS tale, n.d.
        Phillipps MS 24128 Bound in black morocco with "Wat Pringle o' the Yair"
        Related Archival Materials note
        See: Oversize, Box 2, folder 49
      - MARY MONTGOMERY: autograph MS tale, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 25)
        Phillipps 24128
      - MORNING HYMN: autograph MS poem addressed to Mrs. S. C. Hall and dated "Altrive-Lake, the longest day, 1835." (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - THE TWO DROVERS: autograph MS tale (incomplete), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Additional Material, Series II
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - Hogg, James
      - ALS to John Aitken on literary and personal matters, Edinburgh, n.d. [1818?] Mar 4 (Box 1, Folder 28)
        Purchase, 1941.
      - ALS to John Aitken, Altrive Lake, 1821 Sep 27 (Box 1, Folder 29)
        Purchase, 1964
      - ALS to Messrs. Blackie & Son, Altrive Lake, 1834 Mar 25 (Box 1, Folder 30)
        Purchase, 1953
      - ALS to William Blackwood, Mount Benger, n.d. [1825?] Jun 6 (Box 1, Folder 31)
        Accompanied by portrait of James Hogg
      - AN written in the third person and addressed to Mr. Brockie., 1831 Sept 29 (Box 1, Folder 32)
        "Presented to the Authors Club by Frederic Rowland Marvin": printed lines pasted at bottom of letter.
        Engraved portrait of James Hogg tipped on letter. 5x6.5 cm.
        Purchase, 1944.
      - ALS to William Brockie, Altrive Lake [Selkirkshire Scotland], 1835 Aug 7 (Box 1, Folder 33)
        Purchase, 1956.
      - ALS to John M'Crone, Altrive Lake, 1833 Jun 17 (Box 1, Folder 34)
        Purchase, 1966
      - ALS to James Fraser, Esq., Altrive Lake, 1830 Jun 2 (Box 1, Folder 35)
      - ALS to his publisher, Archibald Full[a]rton, Altrive Lake, 1832 Oct 14 (Box 1, Folder 36)
        Accompanied by typescript
        Gift, 1938
      - ALS to [Mrs. Eliza Izet?], Edinburgh, 1813 Aug 20 (Box 1, Folder 37)
        Bound in tan morocco.
        Purchase, 1952.
      - ALS to Mrs. Izet, Edinburgh, 1817 Dec 14 (Box 1, Folder 38)
        Purchase, 1956
      - ALS to William Laidlaw, Edinburgh, 1813 Jul 22 (Box 1, Folder 39)
        Concerning the future publication of his Hunting of Badlewe.
      - AL to William Laidlaw, Altrive Lake [Selkirkshire Scotland], 1832 Nov 2 (Box 1, Folder 40)
        Letter of introduction for Mr. John McCrone.
        Purchase, 1957
      - ANS recommending Mr. Charles Marshall, a tutor, Altrive Lake, 1835 Apr 4 (Box 1, Folder 41)
        Removed from his The poetic mirror, London 1816.
        Purchase, 1930.
      - ALS to Mr. Motherwell, Altrive Lake [Selkirkshire Scotland], 1834 Nov 3 (Box 1, Folder 42)
      - ALS to "My dearest children", together with autograph manuscript of three hymns, London, 1832 Jan 1 (Box 1, Folder 43)
        Purchase, 1960
      - ALS to Robert Purdie, music-seller, Altrive Lake [Selkirkshire, Scotland], 1831 Nov 2 (Box 1, Folder 44)
        Together with proofs of 2 Jacobite songs.
      - ALS to William Saunders, Altrive Lake [Selkirkshire, Scotland], 1834 Aug 9 (Box 1, Folder 45)
        Purchase, 1963
      - ALS to [William Buell] Sprague, Altrive Lake by Selkirk., 1833 Jun 20 (Box 1, Folder 46)
        Gift, 1945.
  - WRITINGS
    - "Memoir of Burns. Chapter I. The Prologue," AM (4 p.); ALS to Messrs. Archd. Full[a]rton & Co., Altrive Lake, 1832 Apr 23 (Box 1, Folder 47)
      With copy of contract for the publication of the "Memoir" on p.3 and typed transcripts of the same; and Ms note to Full[a]rton, Altrive Lake, 24 Nov 1835, announcing Hogg's death.
      Purchase, 1959
    - TALES OF FATHERS AND DAUGHTERS BY THE ETTRICK SHEPHERD No. 2: autograph MS.
      Purchase, 1945.
      See: Oversize, Box 2, folder 50
  - OTHER PAPERS
    - Maclise, Daniel
      - HOGG, ETTRICK SHEPHERD: full-length ink and sepia wash drawing of James Hogg., n.d. [1832 Jan-Mar?] (Box 1, Folder 48)
        21 x 10.5 cm.
        Gift, 1932
- Oversize
  - Series I. Materials given by R. B. Adam
    - Writings
      - JULIA M'KENZIE: autograph MS tale, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Series II. Additional Material
    - Writings
      - TALES OF FATHERS AND DAUGHTERS BY THE ETTRICK SHEPHERD No. 2: autograph MS. (Box 2, Folder 50)
- Additions Since June 1997, Series III
  - HOGG, JAMES
    - Letter: Altrive Lake, to William Thomas McKenzie, 1832 Sep 7; 1 item (1 leaf); 23 cm (Box 3, Folder 51)
      ALS describing hunting on the moors.
      Immediate Source of Acquisition
      Gift, 1997.